<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet
      title="Loading Example Projects from Version Control">
   <intro
         href="/org.eclipse.ui. cheatsheets.doc/tasks/tcheatst.htm">
      <description>
         Before we do anything else, let&apos;s import some example projects into our workspace so that we can explore some pre-built models! We&apos;ll do that by using Team Project Sets (they define a set of resources in a software repository) to import the projects we need.
      </description>
   </intro>
   <item
         skip="true"
         title="Get Ascape Examples Team Project Set File">
      <description>
         Using your web browser, download the following file to any location on your hard drive: http://eclipse.org/amp/project-sets/ascape.psf. Note that the Ascape projects we will be importing are not part of the Eclipse project itself. They are hosted seperatly on the ascape sourceforge site.
      </description>
      <command
            required="true"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.browser.openBrowser(url=http://eclipse.org/amp/project-sets/ascape.psf)"/>
   </item>
   <item
         href="/org.eclipse.platform.doc.user/tasks/tasks-9f.htm"
         skip="true"
         title="Import Ascape Project Set">
      <description>
         We&apos;ll use the team project set wizard to import the example from the AMP website. Open the wizard, browse to the location you just downloaded the file to, and click Finish. The examples will be loaded from the Ascape SourceForge server into your workspace. IMPORTANT: Please note that the version control system (SVN) cannot be bundled with all builds for IP reasons. If it hasn&apos;t been bundled you will recieve errors and a dialog prompting you to install the SVN connectors. Just follow the prompts and try again after restarting Eclipse.
      </description>
      <command
            required="true"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.file.import(importWizardId=org.eclipse.team.ui.ProjectSetImportWizard)"/>
   </item>
   <item
         skip="true"
         title="Get AMF Examples Team Project Set File">
      <description>
         We can also get the AMF examples. Using your web browser, download the following file to any location on your hard drive: http://eclipse.org/amp/project-sets/escapeAMFExamples.psf.
      </description>
      <command
            required="false"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.browser.openBrowser(url=http://eclipse.org/amp/project-sets/escapeAMFExamples.psf)"/>
   </item>
   <item
         href="/org.eclipse.platform.doc.user/tasks/tasks-9f.htm"
         skip="true"
         title="Import AMF Project Set">
      <description>
         We&apos;ll use the team project set wizaard to import the example from the AMP website. Open the wizard, browse to the location you just downloaded the file to, and click Finish. The examples will be loaded from the Eclipse CVS server into your workspace. (If you get a message about repository locations, just click OK.)
      </description>
      <command
            required="false"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.file.import(importWizardId=org.eclipse.team.ui.ProjectSetImportWizard)"/>
   </item>
</cheatsheet>
