<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cheatsheet
      title="Tour an Example Model">
   <intro>
      <description>
         In this tutorial, we&apos;ll run a model!
      </description>
   </intro>
   <item
         skip="true"
         title="Import Example Projects">
      <description>
         If you haven&apos;t already loaded the example projects, you&apos;ll need to do that first.
      </description>
      <command
            required="false"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.cheatsheets.openCheatSheet(cheatSheetId=org.eclipse.amp.escape.loadProjects)"/>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Select Package Explorer">
      <description>
         Go to the package explorer.
      </description>
      <command
            required="false"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.views.showView(org.eclipse.ui.views.showView.viewId=org.eclipse.jdt.ui.PackageExplorer)"/>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Select Model">
      <description>
         Select a model to execute. If you&apos;ve imported the example projects you can use the Epidemic Model. Or if you&apos;ve created your own model, just select that model class instead.
      </description>
      <command
            required="false"
            serialization="org.eclipse.jdt.ui.commands.showElementInPackageView(elementRef=org.eclipse.amp.amf.examples.escape/name.milesparker.epi.Epidemic)"/>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Start the model">
      <description>
        Now we can start the model in one of three ways.
 •Right-click and select &quot;Execute&quot; from the menu.
 •Select the &quot;Execute&quot; from the toolbar.
 •Select &quot;Execute&quot; from the &quot;Control&quot; menu.
If you&apos;ve imported the example projects and want to run the Epidmic model, you can just Click to Perform and we&apos;ll do it for you!!
      </description>
      <command
            required="true"
            serialization="org.eclipse.amp.escape.runtime.execute(elementRef=org.eclipse.amp.amf.examples.escape/name.milesparker.epi.Epidemic)"/>
   </item>
   <item
         skip="true"
         title="Explore Model Controls">
      <description>
         You can pause, unpause, step, restart, and stop the model. Try that now.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Explore Chart View">
      <description>
         Take a look at the Chart View. From here, you can easily change the type of the chart and whether the text is displayed or not. Experiment with different selections.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Select Chart Items">
      <description>
         If you look at the Chart Customizer (Click to Perform) you&apos;ll see that it provides a very quick way to select different chart series to view. Select the chart for the running model and note that the available chart items are updated. Each row represents a statistic that has been defined for the model, and each column represents a measure (i.e. Average or Sum) that is automatically being tracked for that statistic. No need to setup a complex chart series! Click some chart items to see how this works. Note that you can clear all of the current selection by clicking the gray &quot;X&quot; box.
      </description>
      <command
            required="false"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.views.showView(org.eclipse.ui.views.showView.viewId=org.eclipse.amp.view.customizer.Chart)"/>
   </item>
   <item
         skip="true"
         title="Find out more about the model">
      <description>
         If the model developer has provided an &quot;About[model].html&quot; file in a &quot;res&quot; directory, you;ll be able to find out more about the model by looking at the &quot;About Model&quot; view.
      </description>
      <command
            required="false"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.views.showView(org.eclipse.ui.views.showView.viewId=org.eclipse.amp.escape.ide.InfoView)"/>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Working with Agent Properties">
      <description>
         Select an agent in the Graphic View. The Agent will be selected in the properties view. You can even change the value of an agent. Try changin an agent&apos;s status form say &quot;susceptible&quot; to 
&quot;exposed&quot;. You&apos;ll see the agent&apos;s color update immediatly in the Graphic View.
      </description>
      <command
            required="false"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.views.showView(org.eclipse.ui.views.showView.viewId=org.eclipse.ui.views.PropertySheet)"/>
   </item>
   <item
         title="Working with Model Parameters">
      <description>
         You can change model parameters in the same way. To select a model as a whole, click on the chart view or in the open area of the model manager.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item
         skip="true"
         title="View Agent Navigator">
      <description>
         The Agent Navigator allows you to view a tree view of agent contents. You can open up scapes (collections of agents) and view properties for those agents. If you select Agents in the tree view, they&apos;ll be selected in the graphics views; it works the other way around as well.
      </description>
      <command
            required="false"
            serialization="org.eclipse.ui.views.showView(org.eclipse.ui.views.showView.viewId=org.eclipse.amp.view.TreeView)"/>
   </item>

</cheatsheet>
